<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-22T17:03:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">New Cities</title><subtitle>Build Prosperity.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">New Cities Tribune #1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/22/new-cities-tribune-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Cities Tribune #1" /><published>2019-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/22/new-cities-tribune-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/22/new-cities-tribune-1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was contributed by our new community manager, Mitch (supersoup).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to the first edition of The New Cities Tribune: the periodical where we lay bare the development process, offer our thoughts on game design, and open the floor to you, our most invaluable and esteemed community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we’ll be talking about our favorite city builders, and just what it is about them that resonates with us. So kick back, relax, and join us on this little journey, won’t you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image caption-bottom&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/mitchville.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/mitchville.png&quot; alt=&quot;My humble community in New Cities. Pay no attention to the perilous condition of my treasury…&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;My humble community in New Cities. Pay no attention to the perilous condition of my treasury…&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something magical about the city builder. The modern gaming landscape is increasingly saturated with competitive games, flush with adrenaline and high-octane thrills as you pit your wits and reflexes against those of other human opponents. Not to knock such games—I enjoy Destiny 2’s Crucible and Counter-Strike as much as the next red-blooded gamer—but it’s nice to remember from time to time that our favorite hobby has so many disparate and varied facets that keep it fresh and lively. There are games that invigorate, as well as games that relax and allow one to unwind at the end of the day. City builders have set the standard since the early days when it comes to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/166972/cognitive_flow_the_psychology_of_.php&quot;&gt;cognitive flow&lt;/a&gt;, where we lose all track of time accomplishing goal after goal, some presented by the game but most of which we set for ourselves. Wrapped up in the process—that is, until we glance at the clock and wonder where the hours went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image caption-bottom&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/foundation-polymorph.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/foundation-polymorph.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot from Foundation by Polymorph Games, another fine indie city builder currently in Early Access&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A screenshot from Foundation by Polymorph Games, another fine indie city builder currently in Early Access&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of demanding that we destroy, city builders invite us to create. To solve problems, manage resources, and build new cities. I won’t go so far as to say that these experiences are rare, but they’re not something you see triple-A development studios focusing on anymore. It falls to us, the indie developers, to make the sort of games and experiences we really want to see. Hopefully, if you’re reading this, it’s what you’re looking for too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings us back to the question poised at the beginning: what is it about city builders that really resonates with us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the late, great Bob Ross says about painting: “You have unlimited freedom on this canvas.” And I believe that’s true of certain games as well—you’re given a canvas, and the developer provides all the tools and colors you need to paint a beautiful picture. A portrait of life. And perhaps there’s no portrait so grand or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dictionaryofobscuresorrows.com/post/23536922667/sonder&quot;&gt;sonderous&lt;/a&gt; as the city, the hub of humanity since ages past. When we abandoned nomadic existence in favor of banding together into communities, cities soon followed, laying the foundation for both scientific endeavors and cultural growth. Humankind condensed like raindrops in a cloud into cities across the globe, each person adding color or vibrance to the glow of these beacons of civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;video caption-top caption-below&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; poster=&quot;/blog/assets/images/sonder.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/assets/video/sonder.mp4&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/assets/video/sonder.webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;There’s nothing quite so wistful or sonderous as looking out over a city at night&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities represent a microcosm of the human experience, a vertical slice-of-life in which we live, work, and play. They can be as good or as bad as the people who run them—so when given the opportunity, we jump at the chance to prove ourselves to be good stewards of our canvases. We relish the opportunity to manage budgets, please our citizens with strong educational systems, construct beautification projects like parks and plazas, and watch the digital people under our care grow and thrive. There’s a nurturing soul within us all, and there are no better places to practice those instincts than simulation games where you’re asked to create instead of destroy. To build up instead of tear down. And every moment we spend racking our brains for solutions to traffic congestion or finding ways to increase revenue without raising taxes encourages such outside-the-box problem solving in our own lives. It provides a brain exercise that you can’t help but feel enriched by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to pull back from the world once in a while, recharge your batteries, and paint on your canvas—using whatever medium you find most satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now it’s time we heard from you—via &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/udgeB2E&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt;, [Reddit], or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lone_pine_games&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, pick your favorite platform and sound off. What’s your favorite city builder, and why? What about it ignites that spark of satisfaction and joy within you? What would you suggest we could do to bring that spark to life in New Cities? While we can’t promise you that every suggestion will make it into the game, rest assured that we are listening. We want to make sure you have the paints and the canvas you need to paint something truly beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time, happy building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitch&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>supersoup</name></author><summary type="html">This post was contributed by our new community manager, Mitch (supersoup).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Cities Friday Facts #4: Scale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/18/scale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Cities Friday Facts #4: Scale" /><published>2019-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/18/scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/18/scale.html">&lt;p&gt;This week I made several improvements to increase the performance and scale of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major limitation is practical terrain size. The terrain is divided into chunks, and most of the cities you’ve seen in videos and screenshots so far have been 25x25 chunks. Previously, it would take a long time to render the terrain, largely because each tree was individually meshed. Terrain trees are now &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/Vertex_Rendering#Instancing&quot;&gt;instanced&lt;/a&gt;. I also improved the system to randomly place the trees so that they fill the space better, making the forests look denser. The game also now generates high- and low-poly meshes for the terrain for different zoom levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, my machine (which is high-end) would struggle at 50x50 and was unplayable at 100x100. Now I have 50x50 as the default and 125x125 is completely playable. I tested at 200x200 and reached RAM/VRAM limitations; therefore going beyond 150x150 would require some sort of just-in-time re-rendering of terrain so it wouldn’t have to be stored in memory at all times, and possibly a third tier of mesh resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image caption-top&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/map_size_comparison.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/map_size_comparison.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map sizes compared -- 25x25, 50x50, 100x100, and 125x125&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Map sizes compared -- 25x25, 50x50, 100x100, and 125x125&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each chunk is 25 tiles, and each tile is 25 meters, so a chunk is 625 meters on its side. This means that a 100x100 map is 62.5 kilometers, or 38.8 miles, on it’s side. Therefore, a 100x100 map could cover Los Angeles from Santa Monica to Anaheim and Pasadena to Huntington Beach. The San Francisco Bay Area from Berkeley to San Jose and east to Pleasanton would fit quite comfortably in 125x125. 62.5km is just enough to fit the M25 highway which rings London, and all five boroughs of New York would fit in that space too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also improved heatmap performance and save performance. The heatmap performance is dependent on map size. I lowered the resolution of the heatmaps by a factor of 5, meaning a 25x improvement in heatmap performance. As for saving, previously the autosave on large maps caused a slight stutter (100+ms long frame.) I introduced a memory buffer so that saving could be done asynchronously. I also added compression to the save file format, reducing file sizes by a factor of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, we’re only talking about terrain size here, and in its current form the game couldn’t represent the traffic and activity in a city the size of London or LA. There are three kinds of activities which take a lot of processing: building construction/upgrading, vehicle simulation, and routing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/simi-valley.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/simi-valley.png&quot; alt=&quot;Displaying many buildings at once. Instanced rendering dramatically improves performance.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Displaying many buildings at once. Instanced rendering dramatically improves performance.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is constantly trying to add new buildings everywhere there is a zoned lot. It randomly chooses a lot and one of the building designs and tests to see if the design would be a good fit. It tests if there is reasonably flat terrain, no roads in the way, and that the heatmap has the right density and land value for the design. If there are colliding buildings, it tallies the value of those buildings and compares it to the proposed replacement. Improving the performance is really about choosing the right frequency to try adding a new building, as well as making more intelligent guesses for what building goes where. The goal of the game is to make a skyscraper spawn, and therefore this trial-and-error building-spawning process is a very important game mechanic. It will be iterated upon going into the closed alpha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vehicle simulation will be improved in a future update. The current sim can scale to ten of thousands cars, but struggles at the highest game speed. I expect to produce a 5x improvement in this system when I make the improvement. Additionally, there are certain bugs which cause cars to jam up and stop moving. I’ve already experimented with different ways to prevent jams while improving vehicle sim performance. One possible approach is multithreading and reduced simulation resolution with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inbetweening&quot;&gt;tweening&lt;/a&gt; for on-screen cars. Vehicle simulation must be deterministic, and mixing multithreading with strict determinism can be messy. Nonetheless, I’m confident I can make it work. There will be a Friday Facts on this topic in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image caption-bottom&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/thousands-of-vehicles.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/thousands-of-vehicles.png&quot; alt=&quot;Testing the simulation with thousands of vehicles.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Testing the simulation with thousands of vehicles.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for routing, the solution that has worked so far is caching, and I expect more caching will get us a long way, if not all the way to San Jose. Currently routing is done using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A*_search_algorithm&quot;&gt;A*&lt;/a&gt;. One issue is that the cache is not saved to disk, which causes poor performance immediately after loading a large city, but that will be rectified soon. Once I’ve exhausted the benefits of caching, I’ll have to look at more sophisticated routing and graph-processing algorithms. I’m curious how services like Google Maps are optimized. I assume they do a great deal of pre-processing, caching and aggregation. Inevitably I will do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These improvements mean two things: for those with high-end computers, you’ll be able to play larger maps and bigger cities without any FPS drop. For those with lower-end or older computers, this might grant you the ability to play the game at all, with an FPS that’s acceptable. My dream is a game that can support region scale cities, and I will make that dream a reality – promise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re excited about the project, join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/udgeB2E&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/New_Cities&quot;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lone Pine</name></author><summary type="html">This week I made several improvements to increase the performance and scale of the game.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Cities Friday Facts #3: Roads to Prosperity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/11/roads-to-prosperity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Cities Friday Facts #3: Roads to Prosperity" /><published>2019-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/11/roads-to-prosperity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/11/roads-to-prosperity.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;video caption-top &quot;&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; poster=&quot;/blog/assets/images/interchange.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/interchange.mp4&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/interchange.webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A stack interchange&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cities are really about transportation. People choose where to live based on estimated travel time to work, school, or amenities. “Research&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nascsp.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/issuebrief-benefitsofruralpublictransportation.pdf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has shown that ease of access to transport has a stronger influence on whether someone will earn more than their parents did, than the level of crime in their area or whether they grew up in a two-parent household,” according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fwjwePe-HmA&quot;&gt;Wendover Productions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Cities features many kinds of roads, from tree-lined boulevards to high-speed expressways to traffic-corralling one way streets, from stop signs to stop lights to stack interchanges. But currently the only kinds of transportation in New Cities are private automobiles and freight trucks. There are no buses, bikes, pedestrians, trains, airplanes, boats, or even carpools – yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the crowdfunding champaign, there will be a contributors-only vote to determine which new features to prioritize, and most of the candidate features will be related to transportation – so don’t worry, your inner train geek will be satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;video caption-top caption-below&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; poster=&quot;/blog/assets/images/planner.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/planner.mp4&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/planner.webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Designing an expressway ramp in Planner Mode, which allows you to evaluate road designs before paying for them.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to lay the groundwork for these many modes of transit, I needed to refactor and improve “the graph.” The graph is the internal representation of the road system. In the language of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_theory&quot;&gt;graph theory&lt;/a&gt;, the intersections and junctions are “nodes” and the road segments connecting them are “edges”. Each edge connects two nodes, and each node to can connect up to six edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image caption-below&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/2036/&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/2036/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/edgelord.png&quot; alt=&quot;XKCD 2036&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;XKCD 2036&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are only roads and expressways, but in the future this system might represent train tracks, bus routes, airways, and sea lanes. Underneath the graph is the lane system, which tells vehicles where to go. Lanes are also used for routing. The lane system is managed automatically by the game based on modifications of the graph. Sidewalks, bike lanes and HOV lanes would be implemented as special kinds of lanes on roads and expressways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you place an edge (road), the game detects any place where that edge crosses another. It then “splits” both edges by placing a node (intersection) between them. When placing one segment of road, there might be a dozen splits or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets even more complicated. The roads are split in order to conform to the elevation of terrain. Then there is Planner Mode, which allows you to plan roads before paying for them, and this means that splits must keep track of whether roads are completed or just planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;video caption-top &quot;&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; poster=&quot;/blog/assets/images/splits.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/splits.mp4&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/splits.webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;How splits work&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the splits are all resolved, intersections must be geometrically arranged, illegal states must be detected (underwater, too steep, etc), and costs must be computed. Terrain must be leveled, buildings must also be leveled, buildings and lots must be reassigned, new zone-able lots must be allocated, and the lane system must be updated. Finally, everything has to be rendered to screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game has to do all of this in less than 16.667 milliseconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph was the very first thing I implemented, and therefore was most in need of a refactor. There were three issues I addressed with this refactor. Firstly, there were performance issues. I improved performance by making sure that things like rendering happened only once per frame, not once per split. (Performance issues are usually caused by redundant work.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it was possible to accidentally create duplicate, overlapping road segments (two roads connecting the same two intersections). This not only looked ugly but caused further glitches. Now when you overlap one road with another, it upgrades or modifies that section of road instead. In addition, building-by-overlap corrects the direction of one-way roads and expressways, meaning you can change the direction of a long stretch of one-way road using just two clicks – a really powerful tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;video caption-top &quot;&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; poster=&quot;/blog/assets/images/one-way-switch.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/one-way-switch.mp4&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/LonePineGames/lonepinegames.github.io/releases/download/v0.3.0/one-way-switch.webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Reversing the direction of a one-way road while upgrading it to four lanes and installing traffic lights -- all with just two clicks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, it was difficult to predict where intersections would happen. Sometimes roads would go under or over each other unexpectedly. When you actually did want an overpass, sometimes you’d get an intersection instead.  This was particularly frustrating when building expressways. Now the game computes and displays splits as you’re placing the road, making connection points clear. It also computes and displays an accurate price tag for the road you’re about to place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transportation is really at the core of New Cities, and building roads is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gameanalytics.com/blog/how-to-perfect-your-games-core-loop.html&quot;&gt;core gameplay loop&lt;/a&gt;. I’m very glad that I’ve made these improvements. This project is moving forward at HOV lane speeds, so I’m thankful that you’re riding carpool with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re excited about the project, join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/udgeB2E&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/New_Cities&quot;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lone Pine</name></author><summary type="html">A stack interchange</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Cities Friday Facts #2: Sound and Music</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/04/sounds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Cities Friday Facts #2: Sound and Music" /><published>2019-10-04T19:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-04T19:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/04/sounds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/04/sounds.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/sunset.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/sunset.png&quot; alt=&quot;This post is about sound, so here's a pretty image.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;This post is about sound, so here's a pretty image.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time, it wasn’t in my plans for the game to have sound by the time it went to early access. It’s not that I didn’t want sound, but it wasn’t a priority. I can’t recall ever having played a game without sound (or without music), but I also never felt like it was the most important part of any game. For a thousand-hour game, most players will mute the game music at some point and listen to their own music, or a podcast, etc. This week I implemented environmental sounds in the game, and I’m happy to say that I was wrong about it’s importance – sound makes the game a much more complete audio-visual experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music was never a talent of mine and I never learned to play an instrument. I had planned to make connections with a musician and either licence their music or have them compose music for the game. However, when it came time to make a trailer, I hadn’t made any such connection. I strongly believe that a good trailer needs music, so I had to find something. I eventually tried composing music using MuseScore. MuseScore is an application to write songs using a virtual sheet music interface – almost like a front-end to MIDI. After the trailer was released, I was approached by musicians offering to compose music for the game. However, I’m quite proud of the music I’ve made and I plan to make more. I’m also thinking about using Audacity to add samples and effects to the music, in order to make it more full and less “MIDI-like”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video game music is usually built around melodic chord progressions which are plesant enough to not be tedious when repeated for a long time. I still haven’t figured out the arcane rules of chord progressions, but fortunately people who do understand them have written chord progression generators that can easily be found through Google. All of the game music is created by starting with one of these progressions, and then just repeating, modifying, and playing with the pattern of notes and beats to make it interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/menu.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/menu.png&quot; alt=&quot;The main menu. I also added clouds to the skybox this week.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The main menu. I also added clouds to the skybox this week.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had music implemented in the game, it was easy enough to add user interface sound effects (a click sound when you place a road, for example). But for a while there were no environmental sounds. This week I changed that. I’ve implemented a pretty immersive sound environment. There are ambient sounds of traffic, human activity, and life in the city. There are also sounds for the wind, rain, water, and wildlife. I even added a fun retro floppy disk sound when the game starts and on save/load. These additions really add a lot to the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan for New Cities to be your next thousand-hour game. To meet that standard, you’ll need to have a positive immersive experience within the first hour. Even if you mute the game after a day or two, your brain will remember that immersiveness. This will keep the game enjoyable for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re excited about the project, join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/udgeB2E&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/New_Cities&quot;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lone Pine</name></author><summary type="html">This post is about sound, so here's a pretty image.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Cities Friday Facts #1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/26/new-cities-friday-facts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Cities Friday Facts #1" /><published>2019-09-26T15:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T15:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/26/new-cities-friday-facts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/26/new-cities-friday-facts.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi, Lone Pine here. I’m going to start posting weekly updates on the project to keep you guys informed of what’s going on, what features are being worked on, and our progress on the road to release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/city_overview.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/city_overview.png&quot; alt=&quot;A small town, just shy of the 20,000 people needed to officially be a city.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A small town, just shy of the 20,000 people needed to officially be a city.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re new here, I’m working on a city builder called New Cities. Over the last year, I’ve developed a basic city builder with a traffic simulation and customizable 3D rendered buildings. In the past few months I’ve fully implemented “The Prosperity System” which will define the game. It’s a dynamic economic model where neighborhoods thrive or fail based on access to work, shopping, parks, and schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/prosperity.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/prosperity.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Prosperity heatmap. There are two prosperous areas, one around the city center and the other around a small shopping area.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Prosperity heatmap. There are two prosperous areas, one around the city center and the other around a small shopping area.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is based around six “heatmaps”. The heatmaps are Pollution, Crime, Education, Prosperity, Value, and Density. Essentially, Education (plus a good road system) creates Prosperity, Prosperity (among other things) creates Value, and Value (plus Prosperity) creates Density. However, Density creates Crime and Pollution, which have a negative impact on Prosperity and Value, creating a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Negative_feedback&quot;&gt;negative feedback loop&lt;/a&gt;. Negative feedback loops are important to me, since they counteract the explosive nature of positive feedback loops which turn many simulation games into sandboxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/value.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/value.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Value heatmap. There are two high-value areas around the city center and a shopping area. The red in the top right is a low value area, since there isn't a school in that neighborhood. The white buildings are schools.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Value heatmap. There are two high-value areas around the city center and a shopping area. The red in the top right is a low value area, since there isn't a school in that neighborhood. The white buildings are schools.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a player, you have two options. You can buy very expensive city services (schools, parks, police stations, etc) to cut through the negative feedback loop. Alternately, you can build a broad, flat, suburban city, with the intention to grow a dense city center later in the game. I call these two approaches “San Francisco vs Los Angeles.” I consider this to be a kind of morality system, creating the opportunity for different playstyles and different cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image &quot;&gt;
  &lt;!--&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;--&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/assets/images/abandoned_city_center.png&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/abandoned_city_center.png&quot; alt=&quot;Downtown in a declining city, where several buildings are abandoned.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Downtown in a declining city, where several buildings are abandoned.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this game, a city doesn’t just linearly grow. Instead the community behaves like a living organism, emerging out of chaos and always at risk of dying. You’ll have to shepherd your city through randomized recessions in the national economy as well as the consequences of any blunders you make. It will be a more random game than previous city builders, with a more vulnerable budget maintaining a fundamentally unstable economic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be starting crowdfunding in the next two months. One of the tier rewards will be to participate in a closed alpha, which we hope to start before the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re excited about the project, join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/udgeB2E&quot;&gt;discord&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/New_Cities&quot;&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lone Pine</name></author><summary type="html">Hi, Lone Pine here. I’m going to start posting weekly updates on the project to keep you guys informed of what’s going on, what features are being worked on, and our progress on the road to release.</summary></entry></feed>